One of the most common,
complex applications that
people are building using an LLM
is a system that can answer
questions on top of or about
a document.
So, given a piece of text,
maybe extracted from a
PDF file or from a webpage or from
some company's
intranet internal document collection, can
you use an LLM to answer
questions about the
content of those documents to help
users gain a
deeper understanding and
get access to the information that
they need?
This is really powerful because it
starts to combine
these language models
with data that they weren't
originally trained on. So
it makes them much
more flexible and adaptable
to your use case. It's also
really exciting because we'll start to
move beyond language models, prompts, and output
parsers and start introducing
some more of the key components
of LangChain, such as embedding
models and vector stores.
As Andrew mentioned,
this is one of the
more popular chains that we've got, so
I hope you're excited.
In fact,
embeddings and vector stores
are some of the
most powerful modern techniques,
so if you have not seen them yet,
they are very much worth learning
about. So with that, let's dive in!
Let's do it! So we're going
to start by importing
the environment variables as
we always do.
Now we're going to import some
things that will help
us when building this chain. We're
going to import the retrieval
QA chain. This will do retrieval over
some documents. We're going to
import our favorite chat open
AI language model. We're going
to import
a document loader. This is going to
be used to load some proprietary data that
we're going to combine with
the language model. In
this case it's going
to be in a
CSV.
So we're
going to import the CSV loader. Finally
we're going
to import a vector store.
There are many different types
of vector stores and we'll
cover what exactly these are
later on but we're going
to get started with the "DocArrayInMemorySearch" vector
store.
This is
really nice because it's an in-memory
vector store and
it doesn't require connecting to an
external database of any
kind so it makes
it really easy to get started.
We're also going to import display and
markdown to common
utilities for displaying
information in Jupyter
notebooks.
We've provided a CSV of
outdoor clothing that we're going
to use to combine with
the language model. Here we're
going to
initialize a loader, the CSV loader,
with a path
to this file.
We're next going to import an index, the
"VectorStoreIndexCreator". This
will help us create a
vector store really easily.
As we can see below,
there will only be a few
lines of code to create this.
To create it, we're
going to specify two things.
First, we're going to specify the
vector store class.
As mentioned before, we're
going to use this vector store, as
it's a particularly easy one to
get started with.
After it's been created, we're then
going to call "from_loaders", which takes in
a list of document
loaders.
We've only got one loader that
we really care about, so that's what
we're passing in here.
It's now been created and
we can start to
ask questions about it.
Below we'll cover what exactly happened
under the hood, so let's not
worry about that for now. Here, we'll
start with a query.
We'll then create a response using "index.query"
and pass in this query.
Again, we'll cover what's going
on under the hood down below.
For now, we'll
just wait for it to respond.
After it finishes, we can now take a
look at what exactly was returned.
We've gotten back a table
in markdown with names
and descriptions for all
shirts with sun protection.
We've also got a nice
little summary that the
language model has provided us.
So we've gone over how to do question
answering over your
documents, but what exactly is going
on underneath the hood? First, let's
think about the general idea. We want
to use language models and
combine it with a lot
of our documents.
But there's a key issue.
Language models can only
inspect a few thousand
words at a time.
So if we have really large documents,
how can we get
the language model to
answer questions about everything
that's in there?
This is where embeddings and
vector stores come into play. First,
let's talk about embeddings.
Embeddings create
numerical representations
for pieces of text.
This numerical representation
captures the semantic
meaning of the piece of text
that it's been run over.
Pieces of text with similar content
will have similar vectors.
This lets us compare pieces
of text in the vector space.
In the example below,
we can see that
we have three sentences.
The first two are about pets,
while the third is about a car.
If we look at the
representation in the numeric space,
we can see that when we compare the
two vectors on the
pieces of text corresponding
to the sentences about pets, they're
very similar.
While if we compare it to
the one that talks about a car,
they're not similar at all.
This will let us easily
figure out which pieces of
text are like each other,
which will be very useful as
we think about which pieces of
text we want to include when
passing to the language model to
answer a question.
The next component that we're
going to cover is
the vector database.
A vector database is a way
to store these
vector representations that
we created in the previous step.
The way that we
create this vector database
is we populate it
with chunks of text
coming from incoming documents.
When we get a big incoming document,
we're first going to break it
up into smaller chunks.
This helps create pieces
of text that are
smaller than the original document,
which is useful because
we may not be able to pass the
whole document to the
language model. So we want to
create these small chunks
so we can only
pass the most relevant
ones to the language model.
We then create an embedding
for each of these chunks,
and then we store those in a vector
database. That's
what happens when we create the index.
Now that we've got this index, we
can use it during
runtime to find the
pieces of text most
relevant to an incoming query.
When a query comes in,
we first create an
embedding for that query.
We then compare it
to all the vectors
in the vector database,
and we pick the n most similar.
These are then returned,
and we can pass those in the prompt
to the language model to get back a
final answer. So above,
we created this chain and
only a few lines of code.
That's
great for getting started quickly.
But let's now do it a bit more step-by-step and
understand what exactly is going on
under the hood. The first step
is similar to above.
We're
going to create a document loader, loading
from that CSV with all the
descriptions of the
products that we want to do
question answering over.
We can then load
documents from this document loader.
If we look at the individual documents,
we can see that each
document corresponds to one of
the products in the CSV.
Previously,
we talked about creating chunks.
Because these documents
are already so small,
we actually don't
need to do any chunking here.
And so we can create embeddings
directly.
To create embeddings, we're
going to use OpenAI's embedding
class.
We can import it and initialize it here.
If we want to
see what these embeddings do,
we can actually take a look at what
happens when we embed
a particular piece of text.
Let's use the "embed_query" method on
the embeddings object to create an
embeddings for a
particular piece of text. In this
case, the sentence, "Hi, my name
is Harrison."
If we take a look at this embedding,
we can see that there are
over a thousand different elements.
Each of these elements
is a different numerical value.
Combined, this creates the
overall numerical representation
for this piece of text.
We want to create
embeddings for all the
pieces of text that
we just loaddand then
we also want to store them in a
vector store.
We can do that by using the "from_documents"
method
on the vector store.
This method takes in
a list of documents,
an embedding object, and then we'll
create an overall vector store.
We can now use this vector store to
find pieces of text
similar to an incoming query.
So let's look at the query, "Please
suggest a shirt with sunblocking".
If we use the similarity
search method on the vector
store and pass in a query,
we will get back a list of documents.
We can see that
it returns four documents,
and if we look at the first one,
we can see that it
is indeed a shirt about sunblocking.
So, how do we use
this to do question
answering over our own documents?
First, we need to create a
retriever from this vector store.
A retriever is a
generic interface that can
be underpinned by any
method that takes in
a query and returns documents.
Vector stores and embeddings are
one such method to do so,
although there are
plenty of different methods,
some less advanced,
some more advanced.
Next, because we want to
do text generation and
return a natural language response,
we're going to import a
language model and we're going
to use ChatOpenAI.
If we were doing this by hand,
what we would do is
we would combine the documents
into a single piece of text.
So we'd do something like this, where
we join all the
page content in the
documents into a variable
and then would pass
this variable or a
variant on the question, like, "Please
list all your shirts
with sun protection in
a table in markdown
and summarize each one." into
the language model.
And if we print out the response here,
we can see that we get back a
table exactly as we asked for.
All of those steps can be
encapsulated with the
LangChain chain.
So here we can
create a retrieval QA chain.
This does retrieval and then does
question answering over
the retrieved documents.
To create such a chain, we'll
pass in a few different things. First,
we'll pass
in the language model.
This will be used for doing
the text generation at the end.
Next, we'll pass in the chain type. We're
going to use "stuff". This is
the simplest method as
it just stuffs all
the documents into context
and makes one call
to a language model.
There are a few other
methods that you can use
to do question answering that I'll
maybe touch on at the end, but
we're not
going to look at in detail.
Third, we're
going to pass in a retriever.
The retriever we created
above is just an
interface for fetching documents.
This will be used to
fetch the documents and pass
it to the language model.
And then finally, we're
going to set "verbose=True".
Now, we can create a
query and we can run the chain on
this query.
When we get the response,
we can again display it using
the display and markdown utilities.
You can pause the video
here and try it out
with a bunch of different queries.
So that's how you do it in detail, but
remember that we can still
do it pretty easily with
just the one line that
we had up above.
So, these two things equate
to the same result.
And that's part of the interesting
stuff about LangChain. You
can do it in one line, or
you can look at
the individual things and
break it down into
five more detailed ones.
The five more detailed
ones let you set
more specifics about what
exactly is going on, but the one-liner
is easy to get started. So
up to you as to how you'd prefer
to go forward.
We can also customize the index when we're
creating it. And
so if you remember, when
we created it by hand, we
specified an embedding. And
we can specify an
embedding here as well. And
so this will give us flexibility
over how the
embeddings themselves are
created. And we can also swap
out the vector store
here for a different
type of vector store. So
there's the same level of customization that
you did when you create
it by hand that's also available
when you create the
index here.
We use the "stuff method"
in this notebook.
The stuff method is
really nice because it's
pretty simple. You just put all of
it into one prompt and send that to
the language model and
get back one response.
So it's
quite simple to understand what's going
on. It's quite cheap
and it works pretty well.
But that doesn't always work okay.
So if you remember,
when we fetched the
documents in the notebook,
we only got four documents back
and they were relatively small.
But what if you wanted to do the
same type of question
answering over lots of
different types of chunks?
Then there are a few
different methods that we can use.
The first is "Map_reduce".
This basically takes all the chunks,
passes them along with the
question to a language model,
gets back a response, and then uses
another language model
call to summarize all of the
individual responses into
a final answer.
This is really powerful
because it can operate
over any number of documents.
And it's also really powerful because
you can do the
individual questions in parallel.
But it does take a lot more calls.
And it does treat
all the documents as independent,
which may not always
be the most desired thing. "Refine",
which is another method,
is again used to
loop over many documents.
But it actually does it iteratively.
It builds upon the
answer from the previous document.
So this is really good for
combining information and
building up an answer over time.
It will generally lead to longer
answers.
And it's also not as fast because
now the calls aren't independent.
They depend on the result of
previous calls.
This means that it
often takes a good
while longer and takes
just as many calls as "Map_reduce", basically.
"Map_rerank" is a pretty interesting and
a bit more
experimental one where you do a
single call to the language model
for each document. And you
also ask it to return a score.
And then you select the highest score.
This relies on the
language model to know
what the score should be.
So you often have to tell it, "Hey,
it should be a high score if it's
relevant to the document and really
refine the instructions
there". Similar to "Map_reduce", all
the
calls are independent. So you
can batch them and it's relatively fast.
But again, you're making a bunch
of language model calls.
So it will be
a bit more expensive.
The most common of
these methods is the "stuff method",
which we used in
the notebook to combine
it all into one document.
The second most common is the "Map_reduce"
method, which takes these chunks
and sends them to the language
model.
These methods here, stuff, map_reduce,
refine, and rerank can also
be used for lots of other
chains besides just
question answering.
For example,
a really common use case of the "Map_reduce"
chain is for summarization, where
you have a really long document
and you want
to recursively summarize
pieces of information
in it.
That's it for question
answering over documents.
As you may have noticed, there's
a lot going on in the
different chains that we have here.
And so in the next section, we'll cover
ways to better understand
what exactly is going
on inside all of
these chains.